{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This body of water was the destination of Zachariah Gillam’s ship Nonsuch. Henry Green and Robert Juet led a mutiny in this body of water, casting the captain of the Discovery and his son adrift to their death. The area around this body of water was once called Rupert’s Land. A company named for this body of water controlled the fur trade in colonial-era Canada. For ten points, name this Canadian body of water named for the British explorer Henry.",
      "answer": "Hudson Bay"
    },
    {
      "question": "At his villa in Samoussy, Carloman is said to have died either of natural causes or of a particularly bad instance of this phenomenon, possibly the result of poisoned tea. Another death of this type may have been the result of uncharacteristically heavy drinking while planning to sack Constantinople; that 453 AD event occurred while its victim was with Ildico on his wedding night. For ten points, name this condition that is said to have killed Attila the Hun.",
      "answer": [
        "nosebleeds",
        "epistaxis",
        "choking on blood"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. One of these time periods featured the use of Horizontal and Vertical Alliances. An attempt to kill Liu Bang during a sword dance took place during another of these periods, which eventually ended when the Chu lost. The Yellow Turban revolt began one of these periods, whose occurrence often indicated that the Mandate of Heaven had been withdrawn. Confucius lived during one of these periods, which included the Spring and Autumn and Warring States ones. For ten points, name these time periods exemplified by one between the fall of the Qin [chin] and the rise of the Han.",
      "answer": "Inter-dynasty Periods in China"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 1999 biography of this man by Dava Sobel concerns his relationship with his daughter, whom he sent to a convent. This man outlined his mathematical methods in The Assayer, which wrongly disputed the nature of comets. In another work by this man, Simplicio represents the church in a heretical book that was banned in 1633. Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems was written by, for ten points, what Italian scientist who was brought before the Inquisition for supporting heliocentrism?",
      "answer": [
        "Galileo Galilei",
        "either",
        "both names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician secretly profited as a co-founder of the Win or Lose oil company, and largely was able to control the governor of his state, Oscar K. Allen. Dentist Carl Weiss murdered this man, who proposed a net wealth tax to fund redistribution of resources in a plan whose vision was “every man a king.” The “Share Our Wealth” program was touted by, for ten points, what fiery Depression-era Louisiana senator nicknamed “Kingfish?”",
      "answer": "Huey Pierce Long, Jr."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the chapter “A Picture Contest,” an official tries to marry his daughter to a holder of this position by ordering fantastic displays of artwork. A person in this position exiles his half-brother to the coast when the man is caught in an embarrassing affair. A holder of this position becomes blind after having obsessive dreams of his father. Kiritsubo, Suzaku, and Reizei all hold this position in a Heian period novel by Murasaki Shikibu. For ten points, Genji serves as an official in the court of what type of leader?",
      "answer": "emperor of Japan"
    },
    {
      "question": "An artwork comprised of these objects shows four white squares and a white tree on a purple background. A term for these objects provides the alternate name for the Tawagonshi Treaty. Sets of these objects were used to convey rank and station within the Iroquois Confederacy, and they comprise the Hiawatha Belt. A popular legend holds that Peter Minuit bought the island of Manhattan with 24 dollars worth of these objects. Wampum are comprised of, for ten points, what objects made of shells and displayed on threads or strings?",
      "answer": [
        "beads",
        "wampum before mentioned",
        "shells before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This island’s reconquest was led by the Hauteville family, whose Roger II elevated it to a kingdom. Pressing the claim of his wife Constance of Hohenstaufen, Peter III of Aragon was invited to conquer this island during its namesake Vespers. After the War of the Quadruple Alliance, the Habsburgs exchanged Sardinia for this island with Victor Amadeus II of Savoy. For ten points, name this island that Garibaldi’s Expedition of the Thousand unified with Italy.",
      "answer": "Sicily"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man executed a plan developed by Thomas Maitland that he discovered at a Masonic Lodge. After returning from the Peninsular War, this soldier was wounded at the Battle of San Lorenzo; he later replaced Manuel Belgrano as commander of the Army of the North. With Bernardo O’Higgins, this leader guided his army in the Crossing of the Andes to victory at the Battle of Chacabuco. For ten points, name this Argentine general who liberated Argentina, Chile, and Peru from the Spanish, a colleague of Simon Bolivar.",
      "answer": "Jos´e Francisco de San Mart´ın y Matorras"
    },
    {
      "question": "Diane Rawlinson invoked a BFOQ defense based on this piece of legislation during a court case involving the “disparate impact” theory of one of its components. Richard Russell led a group of 19 senators who opposed this bill, for which Everett Dirksen drafted a compromise 54 days into its filibuster. The EEOC was created in this bill’s Title 7. Members of the “Southern Bloc” opposed this bill, which was signed by Lyndon Johnson in the presence of Martin Luther King. For ten points, name this landmark anti-discrimination bill.",
      "answer": [
        "Civil Rights Act of 1964",
        "answers that use Act, Bill, and/or Law"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1906, this venue hosted a silver anniversary lecture in which Mark Twain spoke to raise funds for the Tuskegee Institute. Duke Ellington wrote a three-movement suite depicting African-American history, Black, Brown, and Beige, for his 1943 debut at this venue, which hosted a sold-out 1938 concert that marked the first time jazz was played in a “serious” setting. The New York Philharmonic moved to the Lincoln Center from, for ten points, what legendary concert venue built by a namesake steel magnate in 1891?",
        "answer": "Carnegie Hall"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This clarinetist and “King of Swing” brought an integrated orchestra, including Gene Krupa and Count Basie, to Carnegie Hall for the landmark 1938 jazz concert, which ended with this man’s signature tune, “Sing, Sing, Sing.”",
        "answer": "Benny Goodman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The behavior of this organization was at the heart of the Katz and Olmstead Supreme Court cases. A former employee of this organization, Robert Hanssen, is currently serving fifteen consecutive life sentences in jail. Other employees of this organization included Helen Gandy and Clyde Tolson, who were close advisers of its longtime director. For ten points, name this American domestic police organization headed for decades by J. Edgar Hoover.",
        "answer": [
          "Federal Bureau of Investigation",
          "FBI"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While this man served as Associate Director of the FBI from 1972 to 73, he provided crucial information on the Watergate scandal to Woodward and Bernstein as the anonymous informant Deep Throat.",
        "answer": "W. Mark Felt"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When this man’s son used the pseudonym John Clarke, the confusion led the Prince of Conti to insult him. George Monck fought alongside this ruler at the Battle of Dunbar and was made commander-in-chief of Scotland. John Lambert wrote the Instrument of Government during this man’s rule. After the siege of Drogheda, this man ordered the New Model Army to spare no one. For ten points, name this Lord Protector of England who signed Charles I’s death warrant after the English Civil Wars.",
        "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cromwell won this decisive June 1645 battle against Prince Rupert of the Rhine, a year after the Battle of Marston Moor. The Parliamentarian victory at this battle allowed the recovery of Leicester [less-ter].",
        "answer": "Battle of Naseby"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This site’s inner gallery, or Bakan, is speculated to have been flooded as a form of art depicting the supposed center of the universe. The Preah Poan, or Hall of a Thousand Gods, within this complex, once contained numerous images of the Buddha. This complex was built in Yasodharapura [yaso-dara-pura] as a depiction of Mount Meru during the reign of Suryavarman II, a ruler of the Khmer Empire. For ten points, name this 400-acre temple complex of Cambodia.",
        "answer": "Angkor Wat"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Angkor Wat was originally dedicated to this Hindu god. Depictions of this god often show him resting on Shesha, the king of the nagas.",
        "answer": "Vishnu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One man with this surname was America’s longest serving Ambassador to the United Nations and received Cable 243, which green-lit the overthrow of Ngo Dinh Diem. Another man with this surname balked at Article Ten of a treaty, which raised the prospect of war without Congressional approval; he then wrote a namesake series of Reservations about that treaty, which failed to pass the US Senate. For ten points, give this surname of a Massachusetts senator who thwarted Woodrow Wilson’s attempts to join the League of Nations.",
        "answer": [
          "Lodge",
          "Henry Cabot Lodge Jr. and/or Sr."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Both the elder Henry Cabot Lodge’s wish to sign the Treaty of Versailles with reservations, and Wilson’s wish to join the League of Nations, were thwarted by this group of 13 Senators, named for their complete and unwavering opposition to the Treaty.",
        "answer": "Irreconciliables"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A modern legal definition of this concept is based on the M’Naghten rules, first developed in the 1840s. Defenses based on this concept usually use the Latin phrase non compos mentis to justify actions. Absence of mens rea is used as justifications for lighter punishments when this concept is present. A 1984 act reformed this concept in American law in response to public outrage after the assassination attempt on Ronald Reagan inspired by an obsession with Jodie Foster. For ten points, name this justification in criminal law that requires the defendant to be “not of sound mind.”",
        "answer": [
          "insanity",
          "word forms",
          "insanity defense, not guilty by reason of insanity, etc."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was deemed not guilty by reason of insanity for shooting Ronald Reagan in 1984.",
        "answer": "John Hinckley, Jr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first leader of this empire consolidated the tribes under him with the help of the Ayar brothers. Another man led this empire after his brother, Ninan Cuyochi, died of smallpox. A Dominican named Vincent de Valverde was spared by a man who usurped this empire’s throne after ruling over Quito; that man was defeated at the 1532 Battle of Cajamarca and was the half-brother of its earlier leader Hu´ascar. For ten points, name this South American empire that was conquered by Francisco Pizarro.",
        "answer": "Incan Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man ruled the Incan empire for a few months before Pizarro captured him, briefly let him rule as a puppet, collected his ransom rooms, and executed him in 1533.",
        "answer": "Atahualpa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A central aspect of this document supposedly arose out of one man’s gratitude for being cured of a “mighty and filthy” disease. Reginald Pecocke arrived at the same conclusion of the most famous person who studied this document. That man realized that the author of this document would never use the word “satrap,” and thus declared this work to be a forgery. Lorenzo Valla debunked, for ten points, what document addressed to Sylvester I in which an Emperor supposedly gave Rome to the Pope?",
        "answer": [
          "Donation of Constantine",
          "Constantio Donatini"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Constantine was supposedly cured of this disease by Sylvester. Baldwin IV of Jerusalem also suffered from this disease.",
        "answer": "leprosy"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American Organized Labor",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Group of labor unions that merged merged with the CIO in 1955.",
          "answer": "American Federation of Labor or AFL"
        },
        {
          "question": "Five-time Socialist candidate for President who helped found the American Railway Union.",
          "answer": "Eugene V. Debs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Antitrust litigation used to break up unions, later replaced by the Clayton Act.",
          "answer": "Sherman Antitrust Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strike against a sleeping-car company that was busted by Grover Cleveland.",
          "answer": "Pullman strike"
        },
        {
          "question": "Radical anarcho-socialist union whose members were known as “Wobblies.”",
          "answer": "Industrial Workers of the World or IWW"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former president of the Cigar Makers’ International Union who seceded from the Knights of Labor.",
          "answer": "Samuel Gompers"
        },
        {
          "question": "1932 law that banned yellow-dog contracts and allowed unions to form without employer interference.",
          "answer": "Norris-La Guardia Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Eastern Pennsylvanian Irish coal workers’ society that was infiltrated by James McParlan.",
          "answer": "Molly Maguires or Mollies"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Roman Republic",
      "prompt": "In the government of the Roman Republic, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Chief legislative body of the Republic, which shares its name with a chamber of Congress.",
          "answer": "Roman Senate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Power that allowed either consul to prevent the passage of legislation.",
          "answer": "veto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group represented by the tribunes, contrasted with the patricians.",
          "answer": [
            "plebians",
            "plebs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Office given absolute authority for up to six months during wartime; its holders included Cincinnatus.",
          "answer": "dictator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Original law code of the Republic, named for the number of objects on which it was posted in the Forum.",
          "answer": "Twelve Tables"
        },
        {
          "question": "Office responsible for maintaining morality, as well as instituting a count of the population every five years.",
          "answer": "censor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position just below that of consul, whose holders either presided over court cases or managed armies in the field.",
          "answer": "praetor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Latin term for the series of offices, beginning at quaestor, through which Romans had to progress become consul.",
          "answer": "Cursus Honorum"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Cuban Missile Crisis",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US President in office at the time.",
          "answer": "John Fitzgerald Kennedy or JFK"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet Premier who authorized giving missiles to Cuba.",
          "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of American spy plane used to verify the existence of the missiles, one of which was shot down over Cuba.",
          "answer": "Lockheed U-2"
        },
        {
          "question": "Burmese diplomat who facilitated negotiations between American and Soviet leaders as UN Secretary General.",
          "answer": "U Thant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of ballistic missile system removed from Turkey and Italy as part of the resolution of the crisis.",
          "answer": [
            "PGM-19 Jupiter ballistic missiles",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "US Ambassador to the UN who questioned Valerian Zorin about the missiles.",
          "answer": "Adlai Stevenson II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Urgent command that ambassador gave to Zorin while repeatedly asking him to answer “Yes or no?”",
          "answer": [
            "“Don’t wait for the translation!” quote need not be exact",
            "equivalent descriptions"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "CIA pilot who was shot down was investigating the missiles.",
          "answer": "Rudolf Anderson, Jr."
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A surgeon named Mary Walker is the only woman to receive this award. 864 of these items that were later revoked were awarded by Edwin Stanton to volunteers who stayed on past their (20 pts)",
        "enlistment end-date. Buffalo Bill Cody received one of these awards as a scout in the Indian Wars, one of the few (10 pts)",
        "civilians to be given it. The most common action cited when bestowing this award has been falling on a grenade. The President of the United States personally awards, for ten points, what highest military decoration, given for acts of valor?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Medal of Honor",
        "Congressional Medal of Honor, but"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A sports minister from this country received copies of The Art of the Deal and Where’s Waldo? while meeting with an ambassador in 2017. James Clapper’s visit to this country helped secure the release of Todd (20 pts)",
        "Miller in 2014. Government authorities from this country claimed that botulism, not torture, led to the death of a visitor who had stolen a propaganda poster, (10 pts)",
        "Otto Warmbier. Journalists Laura Ling and Euna Lee were arrested in this country in 2009, but pardoned after a visit by Bill Clinton. Dennis Rodman has made several controversial visits to, for ten points, what reclusive Asian country?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "North Korea or Democratic People’s Republic of Korea",
        "DPRK"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this empire’s “dark age,” its split territory was ruled by two kings, Gotarzes I and Orodes I. This empire’s forces once attempted to depose Tigranes [tig-RAH-nays] the Great by invading Armenia. The Arsacid dynasty ruled this empire, whose (20 pts)",
        "cavalry perfected a tactic of feigning retreat only to suddenly turn around and launch a storm of arrows, known as its namesake “shot.” That tactic was used by this empire’s general, Surena, to deal a devastating defeat to the invading armies of (10 pts)",
        "Marcus Crassus at the Battle of Carrhae. For ten points, name this ancient Iranian empire that preceded the Sassanids."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Parthian Empire",
        "Arsacid Empire before “Arsacid” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this film, India spreads rumors of infidelity after spying her brother embracing the protagonist, who tricks Frank Kennedy into marrying her. In this film, Bonnie Blue dies attempting to jump over a fence on horseback. A barbecue is held at (20 pts)",
        "Twelve Oaks near the beginning of this film, which is, after adjusting for (10 pts)",
        "inflation, the highest grossing film of all-time. Ashley Wilkes is loved by the protagonist of this film, in which Clark Gable played Rhett Butler. For ten points, name this 1939 film focusing on Scarlett O’Hara’s struggles during the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Gone With the Wind"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler employed the sculptor Bek, and the blocks used for construction during this ruler’s reign were known as talatats. This man’s correspondence with Tushratta, king of the Mittani, discussed his marriage with Tadukhipa; those (20 pts)",
        "letters were recovered by Jorgen Alexander Knudtzon on clay tablets at Amarna. Thutmose sculpted a bust of this man’s wife, (10 pts)",
        "Nefertiti, and this ruler was succeeded by his supposed son, Smenkhkare. For ten points, name this father of Tutankhamen, a pharaoh who venerated the sun disc Aten."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Akhenaten or Amenhotep IV",
        "Amenophis IV"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Bribes were given to senior members of this organization from the Konto 5 special fund. Internal dissent between two leading members of this organization resulted in its subjugation during the Blomberg-Fritsch Affair. Claus von (20 pts)",
        "Stauffenberg headed a resistance movement within this organization that culminated in Operation Valkyrie. Gerd von Runstedt was a part of this (10 pts)",
        "military organization, which carried out the Anschluss in Austria. The Kriegsmarine and Luftwaffe were parts of, for ten points, what unified armed force of Nazi Germany?"
      ],
      "answer": "Wehrmacht"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One man with this surname took over James Wilson’s seat on the Supreme Court in 1798 and served 30 years as an associate justice. Henry Clay, John Randolph, and that man with this surname founded the American Colonization Society. In addition to (20 pts)",
        "Bushrod, a president with this surname oversaw the adoption of the Greenville Treaty Line in modern Ohio and agreed to (10 pts)",
        "10 years of peaceful trade with Britain under the terms of Jay’s Treaty. For ten points, give this surname of the first president of the United States."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Washington",
        "Bushrod Washington",
        "George Washington after “president” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Levin Handy took over the business of this man, who died penniless at a New York hospital. A portrait taken at the Hermitage of an old Andrew Jackson was among the entries in this man’s (20 pts)",
        "Gallery of Illustrious Americans. Timothy O’Sullivan, who created the “Harvest of Death,” was among those (10 pts)",
        "hired by this man to carry out his most famous art project. This man shocked contemporary audiences with his realistic depiction of corpses in works like The Dead at Antietam. For ten points, name this photographer of the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Mathew Brady"
    }
  ]
}